So the concept of fundamentalist is essentially linked to
แนวคิดเรื่อง fundamentalist นั้นเชื่อมโยงกับ
the concept of measurement in quantitmecs
แนวคิดเรื่องการวัดในกลศาสตร์ควอนตัมอยู่
before point mechanics was developed
ก่อนที่กลศาสตร์ควอนตัมจะถูกพัฒนาขึ้น
there it was generally a knowledge
นักวิทยาศาสตร์ต่างรู้กันดีว่า
by scientists that if you have a system that this
ถ้าระบบอยู่ในสถานะที่กำหนดชัดเจน
will the term in the state
ระบบนั้นจะอยู่ในสถานะหนึ่ง
and you perform a message on it you're gonna get
และถ้าวัดค่ามัน ก็จะได้
a very well that i mean outcome i
ผลลัพธ์ที่ชัดเจน แต่ในกลศาสตร์ควอนตัม
want to mechanics that's no longer the case you can have
มันไม่เป็นแบบนั้นอีกต่อไป ระบบอาจอยู่ใน
a system that is in a perfectly well defined estate
สถานะที่กำหนดชัดเจนอย่างสมบูรณ์แบบ
and yet when you put from certain
แต่เมื่อทำการวัดบางอย่าง
measurements and it you can get run the outcomes
ผลลัพธ์ที่ได้กลับเป็นแบบสุ่ม
so in order for me to illustrate that concept i be better i
เพื่อให้เห็นภาพแนวคิดนี้ชัดขึ้น
need to bring the concept of super position
ต้องพูดถึงแนวคิดเรื่อง superposition ก่อน
superposition is it's a concept that is not in here liquid
superposition ไม่ใช่แนวคิดที่แปลกใหม่แต่อย่างใด
is is is it's based on assistant displaying
มันขึ้นอยู่กับระบบที่แสดง
several linear combination of states at
การซ้อนทับเชิงเส้นของหลายสถานะ
simultaneously and you can think of it
ในเวลาเดียวกัน ลองนึกถึง
as for example a radio wave carrying
คลื่นวิทยุที่ประกอบด้วย
many different frequencies there's nothing
ความถี่หลายแบบพร้อมกัน ไม่มีอะไร
in human requirement about that
ที่ขัดกับหลักฟิสิกส์เลย
what gives the point on flavor to spread position is the fact
สิ่งที่ทำให้ superposition มีกลิ่นอายควอนตัมคือ การวัดระบบ
of measuring the system
นั่นเอง
so i will instrument with an example
ขอยกตัวอย่างให้เห็นภาพ
imagine you have a system of faros
ลองนึกว่ามีระบบของลูกศร
and you prepare the system
และเราเตรียมระบบนั้น
so that all the arrows are pointing left
ให้ลูกศรทุกอันชี้ไปทางซ้าย
and then you go and you
แล้วเราก็ไปถาม
as the existing the question are you up or down
ระบบว่า "แกชี้ขึ้นหรือลง?"
and us every apple so because the irish point in left can be
ทีนี้ เพราะลูกศรที่ชี้ซ้ายสามารถ
express company described
อธิบายได้ว่าเป็น
as linux of the position between
superposition ของ
up and down you will get
ขึ้นกับลง เราก็จะได้
out terms of our fifty percent up
ผลลัพธ์ที่ห้าสิบเปอร์เซ็นต์ขึ้น
and fifty percent when you ask the question are you open
และห้าสิบเปอร์เซ็นต์ลง เมื่อถามว่าชี้ขึ้นหรือเปล่า
you get that result from their system
นั่นคือผลลัพธ์ที่ได้จากระบบ
and then you can prepare with that at
แล้วลองเตรียม
a different state of the system where have
ระบบในสถานะต่างออกไป โดยให้
there also pointing up and have all their
ลูกศรครึ่งหนึ่งชี้ขึ้น และครึ่งหนึ่งชี้
point in that and you asked the same question
ลง แล้วถามคำถามเดิม
and you get the same result
ผลลัพธ์ก็ยังเหมือนเดิม
there are two very different systems
ทั้งที่สองระบบต่างกันมาก
and you have got this information
แต่ได้ข้อมูลเหมือนกัน
for for for a massive now
มาตลอด
how can you determine what the difference is the
แล้วจะรู้ได้ยังไงว่าต่างกันตรงไหน?
the citizens are very different
ระบบทั้งสองต่างกันมาก
because in the first case you have prepared the system in
เพราะในกรณีแรก เราเตรียมระบบไว้ใน
a pure state many suck western you
สถานะบริสุทธิ์ ซึ่งหมายความว่า
can ask to the system that will give you a deterministic
มีคำถามที่ถามระบบแล้วได้คำตอบแบบ deterministic
not run them out and that question is a you left all right
ไม่ใช่แบบสุ่ม คือถามว่า "ชี้ซ้ายหรือขวา?"
is going to tell you a hundred percent there left
มันจะตอบว่าซ้ายร้อยเปอร์เซ็นต์
in the second case there is no question you crash
ในกรณีที่สอง ไม่มีคำถามใดที่ถามได้
you can ask them give you a hundred percent that then we
แล้วจะได้คำตอบร้อยเปอร์เซ็นต์ เพราะมันเป็น mixture
stick resolve because he's a mixture
ผลลัพธ์จึงไม่ชัดเจน เพราะมันคือ mixture
so if you ask left for right
ดังนั้นถ้าถามซ้ายหรือขวา
going to be around because half of them are up
ก็จะสุ่ม เพราะครึ่งหนึ่งชี้ขึ้น
of the down if you ask apple down
อีกครึ่งชี้ลง ถ้าถามขึ้นหรือลง
same thing there's gonna is gonna be fifty percent
ก็เหมือนกัน จะได้ห้าสิบเปอร์เซ็นต์
how did this this relate to one thing random
แล้วสิ่งนี้เกี่ยวกับความสุ่มยังไง?
so you can imagine that being
ลองนึกดูว่า
similar to flip in a coin is going to be hassle tales
คล้ายกับการโยนเหรียญ ก็จะได้หัวหรือก้อย
but is not like fifty nine coin a toll
แต่ไม่เหมือนการโยนเหรียญทั่วไปเลย
because when you flee because
เพราะตอนที่โยนเหรียญ
the only reason you don't know the result you're going to date
สาเหตุที่เราไม่รู้ผลล่วงหน้า
is because you don't know this
ก็เพราะเราไม่รู้
energy with which a flip that calling the angle moment in
พลังงานที่ใช้โยน มุมที่หมุน
the ambient conditions in the room
สภาพแวดล้อมในห้อง
and so on for so if you knew all those
และอื่นๆ อีก ถ้ารู้ตัวแปรพวกนั้น
variables you could predict castle tale there
ก็คำนวณได้ว่าจะออกหัวหรือก้อย
viables that are hidden today to the observer
ตัวแปรพวกนั้นซ่อนอยู่จากผู้สังเกต
and for a lot of years scientists thought that there was
และนักวิทยาศาสตร์หลายปีคิดว่ามี
similar variables in guantanamo extent will
ตัวแปรที่คล้ายกันซ่อนอยู่ในกลศาสตร์ควอนตัมที่
reveal themselves as as randomness
ปรากฏออกมาในรูปของความสุ่ม
and it wasn't until the
และมันก็ไม่ใช่จนกระทั่ง
seminar work off john bell in the sixties that actually
ผลงานสำคัญของ John Bell ในยุคหกสิบ ที่พิสูจน์ว่า
it was demonstrated that that's not the case
นั่นไม่เป็นความจริง
and now every physicist
และตอนนี้นักฟิสิกส์ทุกคน
acknowledges that there is no hearing
ยอมรับว่าไม่มี
but it will theory that is compatible with going to mechanics
ทฤษฎีตัวแปรซ่อนเร้นที่เข้ากันได้กับกลศาสตร์ควอนตัม
so it is really true that when you measure a system
มันเป็นเรื่องจริงที่ว่าเมื่อวัดระบบ
a nature revealed from the
ธรรมชาติจะสุ่มขึ้นมา
doesn't matter how long i think about that is i
ไม่ว่าจะคิดนานแค่ไหนก็ตาม
will respond that amazing
มันยังน่าทึ่งมากสำหรับฉันอยู่ดี